A Guide to the Sidney Alexander Collection, 1959-1995
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
Sidney Alexander Collection, 1959-1995
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
M 204
Sidney Alexander
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for use without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The original collection was donated to the Special Collections and Archives Department by Mr. Alexander in May 1980; later materials were added beginning in 1996 and a signed Deed of Gift was received in 1997.
Biographical/Historical Information
Alexander was born on March 6, 1912 in New York City. He received his B.S. from Columbia University in 1934 and began his graduate work there. During World War II, Alexander worked with the Office of War Information as an overseas editor and with the U.S. Army Air Corps as a public relations officer. After the war, he worked in a variety of positions as a consultant to The Reporter, editor of The Journal of the United Nations (1952) and as an English instructor for the Italian Air Ministry in Rome. In the 1950's and 1960's, he taught at various colleges and universities in the U.S. and Italy.
Alexander has written several books, an Off-Broadway play and compiled several books of poetry. From 1978 to 1982, he was a Visiting Professor with the Art History Department at VCU and in the Spring of 1984, he returned as an adjunct Professor in the Art History Department.
Scope and Content Information
Collection consists of correspondence, publications and other materials.
Arrangement
Collection is arranged alphabetically and chronologically therein.
Contents List
- Series I--Correspondence 1959-1995
  - Cassell Ltd. 1979-1981 (Box 1)
  - Collected Poetry of Michelangelo 1990-1993 (Box 1)
  - Guggenheim Foundation 1986 (Box 1)
  - Linder, Erich 1979 (Box 1)
  - Macmillan, n.d. 1974-1982 (Box 1)
  - National Broadcasting Co. Chagall's Journey 1985 (Box 1)
  - Ohio University Press 1975-1983 (Box 1)
  - Ohio University Press 1984-1992 (Box 1)
  - Paragon Press 1988-1989 (Box 1)
  - Princeton University Press 1983-1993 (Box 1)
  - Royal Society of Arts, London 1974-1991 (Box 1)
  - Royalty Statements (Box 2)
  - Salem Press 1983-1984 (Box 2)
  - Schweizer Verlagshaus 1980-1983 (Box 2)
  - Stanford University, n.d. 1968-1982 (Box 2)
  - Stanford University 1984-1994 (Box 2)
  - Targ, Roslyn, n.d. 1966-1979 (Box 2)
  - Targ, Roslyn 1980-1992 (Box 2)
  - Virginia Commonwealth University 1979-1981 (Box 2)
  - Publications, brochures and pamphlets (Box 2)
- Series II--Articles, Shorter publications
  - Russoli Preface--Berenson Collection (Box 2)
  - Gattopardo article Reporter 1959 (Box 2)
- Series III-- Michelangelo the Florentine
  - Original manuscript folders 1-5 (Box 1)
  - Original typescript folders 1-4 (Box 1)
  - Bound carbon typescript 3 volumes (Box 1)
- Series IV-- Hand of Michelangelo
  - Corrected galleys foleders 1-2 (of 9) (Box 1)
  - Corrected galleys folders 3-9 (Box 2)
  - Bound typescripts (2 sets) (Box 2)
  - Unbound copy folders 1-2 (Box 2a)
  - Page proofs (Box 2a)
- Series V-- Nicodemus
  - Original Manuscript v. I (Box 2a)
  - Original manuscript v. II (Box 2a)
  - Original manuscript v. III (Box 2a)
  - Notes for first draft (Box 2a)
    1 & 2, 3 & 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12
- Series VI-- Complete Poetry of Michelangelo
  - Poems I (Box 3)
  - Poems II (Box 3)
  - Poems III (Box 3)
  - Typescript (Box 3)
  - Rime M (Box 3)
    II, III, IV, V
  - Introduction (Box 3)
  - Notes--Conclusion, rough appendix fragments (Box 3)
  - Notes folders 1-2 (Box 3)
- Series VII-- Marc Chagall
  - Original manuscript first/second drafts folders 1-5 (Box 3)
  - Photocopy of corrected proofs folders 1-2 (Box 3)
- Series VIII-- Lions and Foxes
  - Original manuscript folders 1-5 (Box 3)
  - Original typescript folders 1-2 (of 4) (Box 3)
  - Original Typescripts folders 3-4 (Box 4)
  - Original typescripts with corrections folders 1-2 (Box 4)
  - Corrected typescript folders 1-4 (Box 4)
  - Illustrations (Box 4)
  - Mixed Bowl (Box 4)
  - Permissions (Box 4)
- Series IX--Guicciardini Storia d'Italia
  - Original folders 1-2 (Box 4)
  - Carbon 66-1979 (Box 4)
  - Targ, Roslyn 1980-1992 (Box 4)
  - Virginia Commonwealth University 1979-1981 (Box 4)
  - Publications, brochures and pamphlets (Box 4)